welcome
everyone. It's great to see some of you.
And of course these sessions,
kind of the nature of the time
zone intersections
is that the middle of the day
is the easiest for most people to attend,
which is why with the plenary
sessions there and then these events,
which people can enjoy at their own
pleasure, our evening events.
And we're so grateful to those of you
who are joining us from time zones
where this is both convenient
and deeply inconvenient, including,
of course, our midnight host here while so
thank you all.
Further ado, I will pass this off
to our amazing exhibitions team.
All right. Welcome.
So I'm here with my co-chair, Dan Cox,
and our wonderful technical assistant,
PD Edgar,
who have handled between them
all of the tech
elements of the exhibition,
since they're better at it than I am.
And so welcome to the exhibition.
It has been a whirlwind as we get
everything sorted and all together.
So we're going to walk you
through a little bit of the themes, show
you a few examples of the work.
We don't have
a preview of everything here
because I do want to go to bed
sometime tonight,
but we will show you some
some screenshots.
Think think about some some themes
and what we found in the exhibition.
So I think the
initial slides are you Dan?
Yes I will take over.
So unsupervised
possibilities was the was the theme here.
And so I'm going to run you through
kind of some various statistical
things about it.
Because
one of the things I like to look at is
how do we compare to previous collections
and previous years we have done this.
There's been multiple versions
of online exhibitions for ELO.
I was kind of
doing a little bit of research
and going up to this, and so I'm going to
walk you through just some stats and also
potentially think about AI coming up
very shortly here.
So to start as a surprise to know
one twine most common platform across
kind of all of our stuff
followed very closely by P5 JS
this year, which was kind of interesting
a frame within that collection
and then Unreal Engine five.
So not not a super surprise.
Unity is in that mix is just slightly
lower than unreal this particular year.
JavaScript, HTML, CSS,
it tends to be dominated by hypertext,
which of course
tend to be within these languages.
React a number of times.
React TypeScript project shows up a number
of times, which is kind of fascinating.
This year and especially and again web
browser show up as a software dependency.
I'm going to pause here
and kind of make the point
if people have not already seen the site,
I know what we've seen a hand few
and by the time you get to the end,
potentially you've already seen this.
I've already seen the site when you go
back to this video in the future,
but we kind of split apart hardware
dependencies and software dependencies.
So you will
when you go to look at the site.
For those of you,
those of us in the present,
and when you're already looking the site
for those of you in the future,
you may notice that some of them require
you to have other hardware
beyond a kind of desktop computer,
so keep your eye on that.
There are some exciting entries that are
not necessarily listed on this page here.
The other thing we did is
this is the first year where we had
a kind of AI disclosure section
as part of the submission form,
and then reiterated as part of a kind of
resubmission form that we sent people.
We had 19 works of a total of 47
that are currently in this collection,
so about 40% declared
AI generated content, AI generated code.
We also asked people to tell us
what models and versions.
So when you get to
those particular sections,
you can look for that towards
the bottom of each kind of work page.
Cloud code, obviously a major player
and a lot of things,
it has already come up as we record this
at the end of the first day
of the conference, I have listened to
nearly every every kind of set sessions
I've been sitting in on all day.
It has come up quite a bit.
I highly suspect it's going to come up
quite a bit in the future,
but kind of also
what part of that collection things
like Midjourney, Dall-E, runway, cap cut,
a lot of the kind of other things
that don't necessarily get as great
a retention for multimedia works.
So image editors, video
editors are also increasingly becoming
part of people's workflow as they move
between models and move between tools,
which is a fascinating kind of shift,
especially from the last couple of years.
One of the other things we let people do
is we let people describe works
the way they wanted in their own,
which is why we get things that are net
art and net art.
One with a hyphen, one without a hyphen.
We also got art game
as one word, art game as a hyphen, and art
game as two words.
So there is a kind of very fascinating to
me that developed around
how people describe things.
So you'll see in this video, the left
hand side is popularity by popularity.
Interactive fiction
obviously reports the top
of how people describe their own work,
but also kind of fascinating
because again, we let people do
whatever they want to kind of
fill it out on the side.
You might guess that whose work it is,
but you can look it up later.
Amazing
work of spirit crushing imagination.
It was a very fascinating tag.
Those of you who might know names
within the community, you might guess who
use that particular one.
But I also like that
we get animated animation of people
kind of thinking about, again,
how they describe their work,
which is kind of, again,
a very fascinating thing.
I'm about to turn it over to Lyle, who's
going to talk about some of the themes,
and I'll kind of contribute as I can,
but these are kind of the things we both
kind of talked about that developed
through our writing of statements.
So each work has a kind
of corresponding statement
that kind of links it to the larger
community, a larger trends we've seen.
And then we'll kind of talk through
and share some screenshots.
But again, there's lots more to look at.
Again, 47 works
we can't possibly cover in a short video,
but lots of kind of very fascinating
themes that developed along the way of us
working on this the last few weeks.
And I'm going to turn it
over to Lyle here, and then we'll we'll
circle back as needed.
All right.
Great. Thank you. So so yeah.
So these were, as Dan mentioned,
the themes that we noticed coming
out of the the works that were submitted
once we'd been through them
and written down our thoughts around them
and seeing where,
where people were coming from
and what their intent was with their work.
And so this is really interesting to me
because, you know, in a time,
you know, when AI is so prominent
and we're seeing it
in such a large amount of our works,
it's really interesting to me
how much it's still we're still trying
to bring things back to the human
and bring things back
to connection and memory
and teaching one another
and telling our stories
and hitting in cultural folklore
through the digital medium
and these sorts of things.
So we're going to give you a little flavor
of some of those.
So if you'll flip to the next slide.
So we do have a number of works in which
we think about meaning
in the structure of the work.
The code as
pardon me, code as literature,
which is sort of part
and parcel of electronic literature.
And it's been around kind of before
we even called it electronic literature.
This from concrete poetry
and experiments with code
way back in the day.
So it's what I love about it
is the absolute refusal of invisibility,
like pulling the code to the surface
and saying,
actually, it's not just construction, it's
not just
in service to literature,
but it can be the interface.
It can be that that space of connection
with the reader itself.
And so we see a few works.
You see a screenshot from bug Cat here,
which is a series of, of code poems
in which you really do need to at least
there's a level of literacy of code
literacy that you need in order
to read this poetry and understand how
the functions of the code interact
with the poetry.
I'm not always completely successful
at that,
but I can I can get a just a little bit
like my reading of Spanish.
And so you get these,
these interactions with, with it's
always a cat, it's always blood cat.
So it's in turn sort of amusing.
But also there's
some existential questions in there
that I'm not sure I was prepared for.
So, this sort of thing is,
is looking at how we express language
through code
and the work and code
as a critical object.
So we can look at there's
a couple more screenshots.
This is the writers project drifts,
which sort of you can
as you can see at the top,
you can set different settings for it
and you in different elements.
You can put in, you write in,
you can see there's a prompt on the left
and you write in and you can set the slide
rate, set the animation speed.
You can set the database where it's
getting the synonyms for that are.
You can see this is a mid animation
screenshot where the.
Poetry,
the words are changing as you write.
And so you're constantly
getting a little bit of inspiration there
to renew the work and refresh
the work through that interface.
And we can go to the next slide.
We may see shopping mall 1999
a couple of times,
just because it is both story
and pedagogy
and code instruction.
So there are parts that are teaching you
to code through the code,
through the story, through the inner
place of face, face place. Hi.
It's after midnight and and also a cat.
Cats appear quite frequently.
I think I'd like to see
our statistic on cats at some point,
but there are a lot of cats, so
this is an excellent exploratory story
that through the exploration of the story
and the space, interestingly,
in one of the twine form story formats,
that doesn't emphasize place
and and movement and rooms in that way,
I think of chapbook more
as like a, a reader Leigh format.
But so it's a it's a very interesting
so cool stuff
playing with the introductory code.
If we had Code literacy and bug Cat,
we definitely get more introductory code
as we learn twine through this piece
and we go to the next slide.
This one I love.
Apologies for language on this one.
This was the least of this one's
particular
screens,
where this one kills you over and over.
You have to be fast enough
to, comment out
bits of the code
because it runs through this code on.
It'll repeat and repeat and repeat.
And then if you get to a bomb, you die.
And the the interface takes
great pleasure in killing you.
So it's this one
was one of my favorites of action coders.
But again,
it's that understanding of code
that is so necessary,
and and fun because it makes it a game.
It makes it something that you need
to read this, you need to understand it.
You need to play with it.
It isn't just, okay, let's by rote
figure this code out and what it does.
I think it exposes the fun
that some of us can have with code that
that feedback mechanism that we have.
It does feel like 99% of my own code
bombs on me and kills me.
And so that one time when it doesn't
and it all works, you're just
you're so thrilled.
It's like you've you've beaten a okay,
the last computer game
I played, which was Mario Brothers,
like you, you've saved the princess.
It's fab. Excellent. All right.
We can go on to.
And feel free to jump in here,
Dan, anytime you want.
There's a particular
piece that you want to talk about,
so we'll move on to the again
after midnight.
The theme of cultural memory.
And so we, I think in
we're becoming more
and more concerned with preservation
and archiving
and making sure that our work is not lost.
I remember way back in the day,
one of my first yellow conferences.
I remember this concern
about loss of of work.
And I think it was
this was around the time that flash,
we were aware that flash was going to die.
And, and we were so concerned
about the, the loss of permanence
and what happens to these works.
And, and I do remember Jason Nelson
standing up at the back of the room
and going,
maybe I don't want it to be preserved.
Maybe it should be evanescent,
maybe it should be temporary,
and maybe that's okay.
And then I went, oh, I like that too.
So but we have still kind of,
you know, we're recording this
and everything's being processed
and stored and all of that.
And so we were creating
this sort of endless cultural memory.
And it's amazing
because we kind of go into it
knowing that there's only so much
that we're actually going to save.
You know, it's the Library of Alexandria
where, you know,
not only is it going to burn down,
but we're going to go to different formats
and we're going to have loss
and we're going to have bugs,
and we're going to have all of this stuff.
So at least if we can preserve what
we can, we still get that, that feeling.
So and one of the workshops earlier,
they asked, you know, if you knew
that you had five minutes
to save something from the internet
that could go into a spaceship
and travel off world,
that would show people
what things are like
and for being human, you know,
what would you grab?
And I think sometimes that's
what some of us are doing,
is we're grabbing something.
We're not going to talk about what
my answer to that was.
But, yeah, is, is we grab
the things that we care about, right?
If your house is on fire,
you grab a the living things, the pets,
and then you
grab the things that are important to you,
the cultural memories to you.
So next slide, Dan.
Well, I would say just to add to that,
I will say, as someone
who's been a part of this exhibition
as well as part of ELC,
this is a major trend across
a lot of electronic literature right
now, is responding to
not only the kind of political moment of
how do we save things
and what is worth saving,
but is showing up in a lot of work.
So the preview, a point that's
going to come up in the presentation,
you know, a little bit into the future
that this idea
recurs of
what do we save and how do we save it.
And you can see it in the works
themselves.
It isn't just the works
that are quintessentially about archiving
and working to archival work.
We see the and this is a trend
throughout Eaglet, which is the
the nostalgic tech.
Right.
So this is for my generation.
This is what we learned.
Computers on this would be an old school
Mac and these interfaces and the text
and the way it all is, it's
bringing us back to a certain stage.
And then it's all about fanfiction.
And the tension
between engaging in fanfiction
and engaging in tech
and engaging in this space
with being a person,
not only a person, but a woman of color,
and not finding
that that space for yourself, not finding
that reflection of yourself there.
So it it is giving us
the fresh eyes on that, that nostalgia
because it's, you know, we don't often
talk about those marginalized experiences
because they were marginalized.
Marginalized.
So between the tags
bringing bringing things
up to the surface
and these memories that mean a lot to us.
And actually, now I will reveal to you
what my, you know, five minute
download thing to, to send off to.
And I instantly said archive of our own
because I think that that shows
you humanity.
I think that it shows you stories
and what we do with stories
and how engaged we are with stories
and how much they mean to us,
and how much we transmit knowledge
and connection through stories.
And it's funny.
Yeah, because we all think of it
as smut and it's that to but it's also
very much about being human,
but it is limited.
So I think that this sort of fills
a little bit of a gap
and gives us an interesting perspective
on that in terms of what do we think of
when we think of history.
Right.
We've already seen
how history of things gets rewritten,
even when we don't intend for it
to be written in a certain way.
It gets rewritten with the dominant bias
of the dominant hegemony.
And so stuff like this can get lost.
So being able to highlight
that I think is great in this work.
Next slide.
And this
is sort of an archival catalog.
This is Mas breezes
Digital t h readings I'm never sure
how to pronounce the things that come in
brackets and things like that.
But this is one entry in
basically an encyclopedic list
of Messi's work throughout the years
and work that they've been involved in
and work that has matured, and work
that has fallen
through the cracks and work
that we didn't know
some of the things about them.
So each one expands into this
little page of and about the medium,
what it was, when it was,
some screenshots, some discussion.
And so this is, you know,
we do hear from
I think we're going to hear from Dini
Gregor Dini garage
group later in the conference
about what we do as artists
to archive our own work, how
we can help this archive process happen.
And this is a great example of someone
who is being really active
in archiving their own work.
And the Paris texts,
as it were, around their work,
which is also really important.
We kind of forget about that
and we think, oh, nobody wants to see
all those old drafts and
and the notes that I scribbled and the,
the timeline that I had on, literally,
I had a timeline on my wall
that was made of butcher paper
for one of my works for years.
And, and
people in the future will love that stuff.
So save it
and make sure it's recorded for everyone.
So this is a great example
of that next slide dear.
I, I enjoy a lot about this work.
It took me a minute to figure it out,
which is, I think kind of
sometimes the fun thing about Elit
is the fun thing to us.
I think it's a frustrating thing
to people who don't yet know illit, Illit
and know the puzzle of figuring out
what the what the trick is
with something when you're experiencing it
for the first time.
And it's something
to this, this notion of illit
being, unpin down, right?
We're always doing something new.
We don't stick with the same old like,
you won't find ten stories with this sort
of formatting and interface.
This is the one that does it this way.
And so this is
it's juxtaposing bits
from Tim Berners-Lee life,
the origins of the internet,
the history of the internet,
early experiences of the net,
what it's become now,
and all of these texts are overlaid on one
another.
As you can see, I've tried to capture
something that we're moving away
from one lexia and into the next,
and that bright spot
in the middle is bright
because it's the texts that are coming.
It's the text
that are going to be coming at you
that you're going to experience
in this work and this sort of,
I wouldn't say a love letter so much as a.
Slices of life, I guess.
Slices come in
in various pieces and you can see
there's mined text, time, tech.
And so it's, it's
this great way that we get this memory
and this biography and this history
and this feel of internet and elit
through that interface
and maintaining that sort of history
and sense of sense of a time
through this interface.
It's it's it's really an interesting one.
So I recommend it.
It took it did take me a minute.
I kept clicking on things going,
why can't I click on something?
So it's kind of a scrolling thing
that you need to do.
So next slide.
I'm also going to let Dan
jump in anywhere here because I don't
do a lot of machine at co-authorship.
So there were a few of these where I went.
I have experienced this now, and
I still don't know what to say about it.
So as we get through it,
I'm happy to let let Dan jump in anywhere
he wants.
Okay. Yeah, yeah, yeah. No worries.
So an increasing trend along with, again,
the 40% of
the 40% of the 47 works is again
increasing trend on agenda
content or using generative
AI to help with code in various ways.
And again, we've got metadata
kind of what people use the models,
but it's a larger
trend to have ongoing conversations
about how this works
where possible workflows for this.
And so we've highlighted
there are other works.
Again, we encourage you to go
check out the entire thing.
But this is kind of three that we think
are kind of an interesting selection
of how people are approaching this,
the first of which I think
is an incredibly engaging,
interesting approach to this.
So ripples is a kind of
very intriguing
use of a kind of centralized prompt
that was then used as a kind of way
to get prompts to other things.
So it kind of meta prompting system
or kind of metaprogramming system,
if you would prefer,
have kind of three different
finished products
that started with a central theme
and then kind of iterated off
in different directions
from different kind of creators here
that dealt with kind of a central idea
and move across them.
Each of these kind of three works
within this kind of own
sub collection is different expressions
of the idea of ripples.
So on your left hand
screen here is ripples
as a kind of ecology
or ecological stance.
We see ripples kind of in the middle
ish here with the green text.
And the person on the train is ripples
as whisper networks, which is kind of
an intriguing idea of thinking,
of kind of ideas moving along a kind of
sense
and down in the kind of bottom corner here
we have ripples is kind of stacks
of textual representation.
It's kind of a virtual stack of things
that you can interact
with to kind of create a kind of 3D
dimensionality to the textural space,
which is a very intriguing idea
of how we think about text in relation
to each other.
All of which, again,
start with the kind of
central idea of ripples in each of which
kind of move their way out.
I encourage people who are interested
in this particular work
to go to the first page and kind of read
through their breakdown of what they did
and how they approached it.
It's very it's very well written
and kind of explains everything.
And then kind of each work is kind of
can be accessed individually.
So it's worth kind of exploring that,
which I think is an interesting idea,
as I was saying, thinking about AI
as coauthor in an increasingly thing
as distance coding as well,
which is going to come into play
the next couple of weeks here.
So similarly here we also see the, the
engagement of what does it mean
to work with AI to create a work.
How do we work through that?
What does that mean?
I will answer my earlier question
from quite a while ago.
If you wanted to know
who had that very particular genre tag,
it went with this work.
So it's a delightful thing
to go play for those of you
who want to kind of engage with it.
But again, thinking about how we engage
with AI in various ways,
I don't want to spoil too much of this
because it's kind of a fun little thing.
And of course, if those of you
who know the author, you kind of
can anticipate the joy you will find
and working with it what you get to it.
So I don't want to go too far.
Similarly, this is another one,
this particular work
grant hotel
here, another set of kind of known
authors coming together
and using a very similar idea
to what we saw in the previous
highlighted work of this.
First, this set of three,
but working through different ideas
of using AI in different ways to become
or AI is co-authorship in some cases.
Again, each of these works in other ways.
And of course
there are others for you to check out.
But this is again
kind of engaging with this.
What does this mean?
How do we interpret it?
How do we work with it, which I think is
part of like bio was saying,
just an ongoing trend.
Every time there's a new technology
or a new kind of interesting paradigm
for us to approach
within electronic literature community,
we're always experimented with things.
We're always trying new forms.
We're always seeing, well, what can we do?
What does this look like?
How do we experience experiment?
And so kind of interesting trends
of a lot of people kind of reinvesting in
what is what is the new thing.
What does this look like?
How do I change it.
So it's always exciting to see both new
and returning faces within this space,
and especially again as we think
about working with AI as kind of coauthor.
And AI is kind of a distant coder,
and especially that meta prompting
metaprogramming approach that a lot of
these works are thinking about as well.
I'm going to go ahead and move on
to the next thing here.
So as we kind of mentioned earlier,
major trend here,
pedagogy and literacy,
we return to this constantly, right?
Many of us are teachers
as our kind of primary profession.
Or if it's on a primary profession,
it is a thing we do throughout our lives.
And I'm speaking experience here
myself as well,
that we we teach and we like to teach
and we teach through our works.
And sometimes it works themselves.
Are our teaching.
Kind of harkening back to
was mentioning that the Rickey's work
is going to reappear.
It's going to also reappear
as part of this
theme, as well as
how do we teach through our work?
How do we teach worth our work,
and how do we teach different works
and how do we preserve them?
I will move on to the.
And over here on the side we see again
twine appearing quite,
quite a number of works based in twine.
This is one of the kind of more
interesting works that is we
remediating kind of a VR interface
in a web interface.
If you don't necessarily
have a VR gear to do this.
We do have some VR works
within the collection,
which is always very exciting to see.
I don't want to go too far into this,
because this is another one
that's best played
and kind of experienced on your own,
but this is shortly into it
of kind of establishing kind of narrative
tropes and narrative structures that it
then subverts
and kind of gets you to think about it.
I don't want to get again to far,
but this is an exciting one.
That kind of gets you
to think a little bit
about VR and the way we express narratives
in different forms.
Here it is again, shopping
mall hierarchy.
If you're watching this in the present
or future.
But here it is again,
kind of teaching how to do twine entwine,
which is always kind of exciting thing.
And using chapbook,
as Lyle mentioned earlier,
when this this appeared
the first time around is kind of always
a very interesting approach, because I
highly agree.
Chapbook is a little more of a
a reader than writerly approach,
but I don't want to go to into my opinions
about storybooks story books, guys.
My opinion is about chapbooks
and story formats,
which I have opinions about all of them.
But debt is another time because I want to
highlight something else.
You are a telephone.
This is a very delightful work.
I know Doctor Johnson is watching,
or at least was earlier.
So hi
at the very delightful
work that I want to encourage people
to go play and read the kind of set up
context for it.
It's a very delightful
P5 work that kind of engages
with remixing as well as kind of language
teaching,
English language learning, kind of second
language learning, all of these kind of
interesting communities here as we kind
of, again, teach through our works.
All right.
So I'm going to move to another theme here
human agency.
Lyle, do you want to switch back in?
Sure, I will do that.
I enjoyed the
where is the sad rabbit on that?
That screen? Well, the rabbit is sad.
My chickens staged escape today,
so that's why chickens are on the brain.
So Ellis Ellis is relevant to me.
So human agency,
as I mentioned earlier, human
as we find so many works and so many
that are really digging into the machine,
really digging into the code, really
working with AI, that sort of thing.
It was interesting to us
how much the work tried to turn back
and bring the human back into the machine,
whether that's through
reader participation, reader direction,
making sure that there's a conversation
happening,
that there's some sort of connection
and there's some sort of control,
I think goes beyond
Illit a little bit right now
when so many of us are in situations
and environments and governments where
and workplaces
where we have very little control.
This notion of bringing
control and agency and choice and feeling
like what you do is important
is, is kind of a big deal.
So in these works where it can be so easy
to become distant from the literature,
from the feelings, from what's happening
in the work, that that works have brought
human agency back into it,
I think is pretty significant.
So we can go see a couple of these works
on the next slide.
This one is this one is in ink,
but it's that very still
that very hypertext
choice based narrative.
And it's this is that simple agency
having choice,
having a narrative that we understand
and focusing on that narrative
and then just having some simple choices.
We tend to often brush over these,
especially when we start thinking about
prizes and selections and collections
and things like that.
And we kind of go,
oh yeah, I've seen hypertext before.
Hypertext has been around for ages,
and there's there's a reason
we keep coming back to it.
There's a reason we keep using it.
There's a reason that twine is so popular
in our collections.
There's a reason that it has persisted
as well as ink.
These formats work, and they work
because they don't disconnect us
from our readers.
They invite our readers in.
Our readers understand
what we're doing with the story.
They feel like they know enough to engage,
and they have a role,
and they understand their role.
And when so much is overwhelming,
I think these sorts of works become very,
very important to us.
And I look back at works
like see you later
from Dan Het that won the New Media
Writing prize a few years ago,
which is just simple, straightforward
hypertext, but so beautiful.
And so these kinds of works,
and this one as well,
really is about that is about story
and connecting with the reader
and not making it overly complex
so that that connection can be there
and the reader can feel their role in
that story is really important.
So we can look at the next one.
I enjoy this one.
The dean is asking a question
what is the name of written?
And that one was read manifest.
Yeah.
Read manifest
from yellow de Mendonca Saleem.
So it will be in the.
You'll find it in the collection that
I believe Mark linked to in the chat.
And we will give here
as part of the slides.
So on the video you shan't miss it.
Yes. Hi.
I live in Britain.
Shan't we go to the next slide.
I do love this one.
This is another
that can go in multiple categories.
And I kept kind of moving it around
in the themes going
oh we could talk about it here
and we can talk about it here.
We can talk about it there.
This is one
where it's obviously pedagogical,
but it's also ecological
and it's also resistant,
and it's also human agency,
and it's also multiplicative and layered.
And so it can go in
lots of these categories.
But it's I really enjoyed playing this
because I could go
and I could do something.
So there's little game elements.
There's story elements, there's learning.
And again even though it's it's
on that level of it's
obviously intended for a younger audience.
Great.
You know,
we're not going to persist as a field
unless younger
audiences are coming with us.
And this sort of engagement
where they feel like they're part of
the story, is normal for them,
that everybody knows
the toddler tapping us,
you know, the fingerprints on the screen
because they expect all screens
to interact with them now to have their,
you know, this is this is their now
they're bored book, their pop up books.
They're interactive books.
And so this is what we're giving them.
And I think it's wonderful
to see works like this from
authors who understand the
medium,
because quite often we get stuff for kids
that is written and created by,
you know, people who say, oh,
this new thing, let's do this new thing,
let's make an iPad app, let's do this.
And they don't really think about
how the medium works
for this particular instance,
and how it's going to be interacted
with in these sorts of things.
So, you know,
this is also something that we can do
to let our kids
and let young people and let people
who just need to learn about ecology.
I enjoyed this.
I mean, yes, I have the mentality
of a 12 year old sometimes, but,
it's just a fun work
is scruff stay next slide
okay, so get lost.
This one is again
something that could have
fallen in multiple categories.
But this one the poetry changes.
It's hard.
This one putting it in a screenshot
diminishes it.
So I should have made it
an animated GIF or something like that.
Might have required more brainpower
than I apparently had today.
If you look at discord.
And so
this the poetry kind of keeps, you know,
asking about the world,
about your place in the world and even
and so you interact with this
and you regenerate
works and words and phrases
and it's asking you questions.
And I think this is a writerly tech.
This is a very writerly text
to ask a reader questions.
It's the it's the
base of
human agency and human interaction, right?
When I run workshops
and of people who are trying to network,
I say, however you introduce yourself,
you want the person that you're speaking
to to have questions about you.
You don't want to go on a lecture series.
You want to say something about yourself
that makes them interested
and has them ask questions.
So by asking the reader questions, by
making them think about this world
and this the sensations of the poetry,
we're engaging in agency,
even if it's less of the
I'm going to go here, I'm
going to collect this, I'm
going to do this.
I'm going to enter in some text here.
I'm going to do something here.
There's still agency here.
It's still about the human here
and human choices and interaction
in this particular piece.
Next.
Yay resistance through multiplicity.
This is where I get
I get really excited about the works.
The this is where I'm talking about
it as resisting that easy categorization,
not only in terms of John
and in terms of form and,
and how people interact
and how we understand
what is lit and what's not.
You know,
there's lots of things that I argue
are that that not everybody agrees
with me, but.
It's again, it's this resistance.
So we have
hypertext fiction
and code, poetry and documentary
practice and immersive environments,
and then we have archival
projects and browser games and all these
different things.
Sorry. Am I
I thought I heard something that's
all right.
So and it's part of what we do.
The other thing that we do is
we use the layers,
the different spaces
that we have, the multiple meanings
that we can build into to our work,
the different modes of communication,
the different styles,
the different interaction
and haptics and gesture.
We use that to say something more
about our world
and to help people understand things
and to push back against our world.
So literature, art
have always done this,
you know, it's always been about
how can we make a better world
or a different world
or world
in which I can finally fit as a person
and not not me personally, the royal I,
I don't fit and that's fine.
So but but trying to make things better
in some way, trying to push back.
And so whether it's through, you know,
push back on a tiny little part of a
to say, I'm here, this is me,
or to push back against world events
and things that are happening
so we can move to the next slide.
And this is part
of a series of VR poems
where you explore an environment.
So so you're in this sort of
I don't have VR,
so I experience them
in 2D like this and exploring them
and this, this, these bits of poetry
kind of appear in the environment,
overlaying
the scenery, overlaying the environment,
overlaying things.
And lots of times they're about,
ecologies, sometimes
they're about memory,
sometimes they're about all of this,
you know, you can see even in this,
the one side is green, one side is not.
Who's ghost are you?
So the fence is not electrified,
but it's still very imposing, you know,
and so it's
the different versions of power
that we think about are in this text.
And so it's an exploration
of literally it's a space.
This is taken from real 360 video.
And the poetry you find, the poetry
you explore to get the poetry.
And I think that that is
you don't seek out the poetry
unless you care about this issue,
and then it makes you care more about
what they're talking about, care
more about power and what power means.
And you feel it through that environment.
So this is that bit of resistance
coming through this work.
Next slide.
Oh I had fun with this one.
We did we did a bit with this one
at the unconference earlier this year.
This one has this is one
where you have to like you're a spelunker.
You are an archeologist
digging in and brushing
little fossil teeth
with your toothbrush sort of thing.
Because as you can see along the left
and along the right,
there it is a huge archive of
files and documents and the story,
and it's about digging into those of you
who like archival digging
and digging into the language
and comparing documents
and the sort of Wikileaks type stuff.
That's what this that's what source is.
So it's uncovering
sort of it to me,
the core of it is truthiness,
which is is about
how do we craft the story
of what's happening and who we are
and what justification is for things.
So it's the interplay of government and
government workers, you know,
not not the politicians,
but the ones who actually get things done
and the files and then justifications
and then redactions that then cover up
mess ups and all these different things.
And so you sort of dig as well as media,
what, what choices do
media make about what they release to us
and what they don't?
So this one is all about
that resistance through the interface
and through digging through it.
And I don't even want to know
how much time was spent to build this,
because it kind of
fries my brain to think about, like,
I always have to map things out
and know how everything links up
to everything else.
And I don't know how many roles
of butcher paper this would have taken me,
but this is a really useful piece
and a useful peace.
Peace to teach those sorts of that sort
of resistance, that sort of truthiness,
that sort of how media and government
and spin gets put on things and different
notions of what we're going to release
to the public and what people see
and what we can make a
story and that sort of thing.
Next.
This
one to this one was really effective.
You, this this takes the form of
a very popular form of digital fiction,
which is visual novels,
which are far more popular in East Asia
than they are about here, but are emerging
and are still a very popular here.
Usually you're go it's some sort of they
they're also called dating sims.
And so they're little romances
that you you go in.
So the premise here is that
you're starting on a first date and you,
you're a little bit nervous.
And so you've hired
an alpha male dating coach.
And as you can see
the dating coach says,
oh, let's get you laid, King.
It's gross.
But it's it goes all in on that
and you make choices.
You've got agency here.
So you can say, you can say nope okay.
Or you can go,
yeah, let's jump into this full force.
Let's be really frat boy. Gross.
And so you can see
the influence of this culture
and what happens.
And so it's it's a fun little dating sim.
And it seems like that to begin with.
And then you dig in and you're like, okay,
there's a lot of toxic masculinity here.
There's you know, we sort of
see the, the red pilling that happens
and the influence that
this type of attitude can and does have.
And so it's it's that surface fun game.
But underneath it's you know,
this is why, you know,
violence against women is so high
and these sorts of things.
So an excellent piece here as well.
Next.
Excellent connection.
Dan, do you want to take over for a minute
or do you want me to keep.
I'm happy to take over. Yeah, yeah.
Take a break.
Yeah.
So we'll talk about this theme
and then we'll move this into
just kind of place people
where we are in this presentation.
This is the last of the kind
of major themes.
And then we'll talk a little bit
about the site and I understand
unfortunately I can't see the comments
and run this on this screen.
So I've not been watching the chat,
but I'll look at it here in a second.
But we will kind of talk
about the functionality
and everything at that point.
So we are coming towards the end.
For those of you
who might be late into your night
or early into your morning,
perhaps you're watching this
in the future.
Who knows?
Perhaps you're watching this. The past.
I don't know if you're a time traveler.
Who am I to know?
But yes, who am I to know?
We are a connection.
I'm reminded earlier
I was working with a device,
and anytime you unplug something,
it kind of spins and looks very sad.
And it's just looking for connection,
looking for connection,
looking for connection.
And of course, every time you look at it,
you can't help
but think, so are all of us.
But this particular theme, as we see
kind of listed
towards the side here, engages
with how we interact with things.
Our connection
to interfaces, our connections
to systems, our connection to each other
and throughout this kind of
real reintegrate some of the themes we've
seen in other places as well.
A common theme, and you see it
particularly in this work,
is a kind of remediation
of earlier versions of interfaces.
We saw it with the previous work
a lot earlier.
We're seeing it with this work.
I've seen it in a number of other
works of kind of reflecting back
to potentially a more idyllic time,
even if that's perhaps nostalgia.
But I kind of look back
of how we integrate things.
This is also very fun thing
to play around with,
so I don't want to spoil too much,
but notice the kind of system notices.
For those of you
who existed in the early versions
of the web of kind of pop up ads
and other things.
It's a fascinating kind of meditation
on what that might mean and what a
what a computer virus may
or may not mean as part of the title, but
it is a fun
it's a fun thing to go and interact with.
We now move to quantum entanglement,
which is a very fascinating piece.
I see reaction to this.
Yes, we we both kind of interacted
and played with this.
I will forewarn people
this is a kind of upward scrolling piece,
so if you don't quite figure it out,
you do need to kind of scroll.
It's experienced a little better
on on a kind of phone or digital device
that has that layout.
So you can kind of use your fingers
to scroll,
but clicking and dragging works
just as well to kind of engage people.
Things move in and out.
It's supposed to be a kind of
look at the quantum
lovers of a protagonist,
but it kind of moves things around.
It's very kind of delightful, playful in
that way, intermixing English and Spanish.
So if you're
if you're slightly bilingual,
you can kind of experience
a kind of greater
understanding of the layers
kind of going on.
Quite a fun work by a number of authors
that are kind of included
within their including, you know, Mark
Reno was quite known within the community.
So I encourage you to go check it out.
And again,
kind of go through the whole thing
and you will know
when you have gotten to an important part,
because it will tell you, like, hey,
things will start to change,
but you experienced the main part.
It will kind of tell you
that you are towards the kind of finite
of the infinite that extends into.
But it's quite a delightful
kind of moving through all these different
things and engagement with that.
But yes, it's quite interesting and
not a lot from this particular platform.
This is a scroll cinema platform.
I've seen works from this before,
but it's always intriguing to see.
Speaking of kind of connection
and platforms
and interesting platform
piece of this, of this connection.
We increasingly
have seen kind of conversations with AI.
This is an interesting example
that was kind of a
might be thought
of as a small language model
that kind of develop on its own works
and has kind of fed into a conversation.
You can have this, in my mind,
kind of hearkens back to earlier attempts
at dialog systems and video games,
where along the side
it will give you kind of list of topics
where you can kind of choose
a topic and engage with the kind of model
which is kind of moving through its own
philosophical approach to things.
But you also typed a approaches to it
kind of in a little chat box.
I had fun playing with this, where
I kind of chose a very more high
minded philosophical conversation with it,
and then I had an attempt to kind of,
I don't
know, a low end conversation with it.
I just fed it junk
just to see what it would do.
And it kind of kept doing its own thing,
which was very fascinating, kind of,
and in some cases ignored what I typed
because I was feeding it
kind of garbage to see what happens.
So these kind of things
are always kind of fascinating.
This is one again
leaning towards a very specific direction.
You'll notice
the subtitle of semi-private.
I know it's a little bit
faded text on the screen.
It might be for y'all as well
but semi profit of a non religion.
So that does kind of play
into the philosophical connection.
That is a type attempting to make.
But it's quite a fun thing to play with.
Again moving with topics
and looking at other things.
So if you get a chance,
check this out as well.
So that will move us through the main
themes we have highlighted.
So if you are watching this video
in the future,
go back to that kind of table of content
slide in case you missed something.
So to kind of move into the last chunk
of this here, and then we will have
some some time for Q&A at the end
if people have any questions about things.
But this is a site,
I know it's
been shared among other things,
but this is the site right here,
following the same general URL
path of the 2024 and sharing in the color
palette of the entire site.
And you'll notice kind of a similar
layout here of our home and our search
and our about and some new functionality
that is new for this particular edition.
Before I go
too far and talk about that though,
which I do want to close on,
so we can kind of open it up to questions
potentially about it
and about other works.
I do want to highlight that this uses
the Elms metadata schema
that was developed by the next.
It is a variant of it,
so it is very close but not quite.
We added I will say I, I added
the artificial intelligence section.
So there's kind of an additional section
of that as well as more or merged
in some of the stuff that had been used
for literature, volume four.
So creator keywords and things like that.
So it's a little bit of a hybrid
of those two approaches.
So if you're like, oh,
this looks very familiar to other things.
Hopefully it does.
But it doesn't corporate a lot of things.
This is a slightly more traversal
traversal forward approach.
So you will notice
kind of in the middle of the page
as you look at works will be an image
kind of cover or representative image
and also a traversal work.
The traversal works I do want to
highlight was made by our traversal team,
which includes Alyssa and Rickie from UCF.
So please give a hand to them
if you happen to see them
throughout other things here.
And they might be here tonight.
I can't quite see everyone in the gallery
here, but they did fantastic work
to kind of record those traversals
along with me, to kind of capture
a lot of things, I will say,
because we gave people the option,
a lot of people
submitted their own traversals
or their own previews and in some cases
kind of really nice trailers.
So that's kind of intermixed
in all of this,
which is always a very exciting thing
to see of kind of intermix of people
playing the work
for the first or second time and then very
professional things into that mix.
And so we will move through that.
So speaking of the last thing
before I turn this over to Q&A playlists.
So one of the things John Murray,
who did the major work on this
initial model.
Hi, John.
One of the things in talking with John
that John had said,
it would have been a nice thing to have in
an earlier version
was some type of way to remix
or select things or talk about things,
and in talking with other people
about kind of what things they wanted.
One of the major things
that reoccur about collections like this
was an ability to have a kind
of pedagogical function to it, like,
how can we make a sub collection or easily
sort things?
And, you know, you could always share
links, direct links to works.
But one of the things I put forward
in this, based on that feedback
was the ability to create playlists.
You'll notice
a playlist is kind of a top level item.
You can go in, you can name a playlist,
you can select
any of the works
you want based on John was.
So that's that focus on me.
There is a standardized list of keywords
which are part of the star system.
So you'll notice
kind of recurring things there.
And there's a standardized set
of kind of platforms and other things.
So if I work was tagged with key five JS
and another work was P5
js with no dot, I kind of standardized
those together and kind of reunited them.
So there is a focus on a me approach,
a kind of more standardized approach,
and then a normalized approach.
And you can also just sort things by here
and all kinds of other categories.
So whoever this this allows people
to kind of remix things.
This is the unsupervised approach
to this particular collection
where you can make your own playlist.
Potentially people are already doing that
and share those.
And then when you load it
in, it'll load in that kind of subclass
and then share what filters
were used to do that.
So hopefully that allows people
to use this for a pedagogical angle
to kind of remix
and reshare a lot of this.
And I will also right
before I turn this over to Q&A,
also say that this is currently
kind of in a feedback stage.
So if you're really enjoying this
or you wish it had more,
or you wish it had less, I don't know.
I'm willing to kind of hear that feedback
because we would like to reuse this
approach for Electronic Literature,
volume five, coming out next summer.
I am also going to tag in that we
I am working towards.
This is a me project at the moment,
although I would love hope
we're working towards
making this open source software.
That was a kind of go
of a previous version in 2024.
It didn't quite get to it, but this is
very, very close to being open source.
Kind of.
It's been improved upon.
I wouldn't say that sounds weird.
It's been worked upon, polished.
Additional testing was added.
I see John laughing.
It was an improved upon John.
It was great.
It was fantastic.
Bones I just changed a slight thing,
been improved upon, iterated on.
And we are.
I am working towards making it open source
so other people in the future
could use the same approach.
I will say it's a little tricky
at the moment.
That requires kind of
knowing how everything works,
but the hope is to kind of
get it out there
so other people can be using it
as well as there is work towards
the future of archiving the entire code
of the site of this particular
online exhibition for 2026,
also the online exhibition for 2024,
and then working backwards.
There's kind of
an ongoing project of that.
So as we kind of move
past this conference and into the future,
there will be work to kind of potentially
organize the source code
of all of these things.
So again, as we said,
we are preserving the work for the future,
hopefully making some people
don't necessarily reinvent the wheel.
So, Lyle, unless you want to do a yes
and I will throw it to Q&A,
I want to do a yes and I want to say yes.
And a huge round of applause
for Dan for the tech work on this.
It has been absolutely stunning
and I had nothing to do with it.
So massive round of applause
for Dan and for John's previous work.
Yeah.
I'm always amazed by the work
that these guys do, and I.
I'm not worthy in true
Wayne's World fashion.
So yes, anywhere I can help
with this project from my end,
I'm really good
at documentation, so if I can help there,
please let me know.
And yeah,
and I'm happy to open it up to Q&A.
Or we all go to bed.
Any questions any.
Yeah.
On that note of positivity,
I think we're at a great point
to end day one.
So our video team is already hard at work.
The keynote and some of the other
sessions are popping up.
You can find them for the stars
repository interface
or through my website, which ever
you find less painful to navigate.
And the exhibitions
are also linked through the site,
so you have plenty to explore tonight
if you have any energy left.
Or hey, if it's the morning, there
have lots
to look at and our goal is to have
as much of today's content
available tomorrow as possible.
So if you missed sessions
or you're hearing about things
now that you wish you had been a part of,
please take a look at.
Spend some time
exploring from the future as well.
And thank you again
to our amazing exhibition team.
There would not be an exhibition
without your efforts.
Truly, this year is incredible and we,
the work
and everything you've accommodated and the
the work of preservation and documentation
of metadata is just wonderful.
So thank you so much for doing this.
Difficult mostly
when it's totally uncompensated labor
for the future of the field.
Yes. Thank you so much to the students
who did work to PD, to Dan,
who kept me sort of on track.
I know that I am a cat
who is hard to wrangle.
So thank you to the whole team
and thank you, Lyle, for doing things too.
I'm not going to let you get away with
just taking me and closing this to.
You. Did a lot of work. We both did.
Both did a lot of work.
It's in there.
All right, well, whatever you.
I accepted my compliment.
You didn't accept yours.
So that's that's, you know,
what are we saying here?
Also, I'm going to look,
if nothing else is the goat for sure.
Like, y'all have no idea.
But that's a whole other thing for this.
Anastasia. Edit. Kill us. Just end it.
All right?
I'm. I'm putting this session to rest.
The discord is open.
There are lots of exhibits to check out,
and unlike the physical galleries,
they won't close down and nobody else
is trying to get to your screen.
So there are some advantages here
for appreciating, especially long form.
As someone who's gone
to those past exhibitions and been sad
because I could only get through a tiny
fraction of what was in front of me.
So please take your time, enjoy and have
a lovely night, morning, afternoon
and we'll see you all tomorrow.
Bright eyed and bushy tailed.
Good night.
Good night everyone. Bye bye.